Guide to the Max V. Mathews Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Audiovisual materials
  - Photographic slides
    - Computer composing (Box 15)
    - Violin (Box 15)
    - Conductor program (Box 15)
    - Conversion study (Box 15)
    - Fase (Box 15)
    - Scaling (Box 15)
    - Prog Inst (Box 15)
    - Anechoic chamber (Box 15)
    - Behavioral research history (Box 15)
    - Music V (Box 15)
    - Speech synthesizer (Box 15)
    - Shepard's tones (Box 15)
  - Audiorecordings
    - Swansong, 1967 Dec 17; 9.01; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Webern Bagatellen - Paris String Quartet, 9.02; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Improvising Machines master, 1971 Feb; 9.03; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Resonators and Brass Violin - demo tape - master, 9.04; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Working tape: Improvising Machines - Imp for Running Man, 1971 Feb; 9.05; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Emmanual Ghent - Innerness, 9.06; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Ravel experiments, 1976 Aug 22; 9.07; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Elephants Can Graze, 1972 Mar 1; 9.09; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Elephants Can Graze, 1972 Mar 12; 9.10; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Masquerades and Pergolesi master recordings, 1964 Sep 19; 9.11; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Conductor Program Demo, S.W. German Radio, master, 1976 Aug 10; 9.12; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Slider, two copies, 1967 Nov 5; 9.13; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Pierce's tape - demonstration - some aspects of sound quality, 9.14; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Swansong - tape A, 1967 Dec 12; 9.15; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Emmanuel Ghent -- Fission, Our Daily Bread, Supernova, L'Apres Midi d'un Summit Meeting, 9.16; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Shepard's Tones, master tape, 9.17; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Gerald Strang, 1969 Aug 28; 9.18; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Gerald Strang, Baroque Variations, Synclavion #4, 1982; 9.19; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Gerald Strang, Compusitions Synthons, 1969; 9.20; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Swansong, tape B, 1967 Dec 16; 9.21; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Mathews - Graphic I, 1966 Aug 29 - Sep 5; 9.22; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Mathews - Graphic I, 1966 Jun 28 - Jul 30; 9.23; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Mathews - Graphic I, 1966 Aug 3-20; 9.24; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Mathews - Graphic I, 1966 Aug 20-29; 9.25; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - 8 Tone Cannon - Pierce - master recording, 9.26; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Slider - working tape #1, 1967 Nov 5; 9.27; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Mathews PB 250 runs, 1965 May 11 - Jun 30; 9.28; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Gerald Strang - Compusitions #9 and #10, 1972-1973; 9.29; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Improvising Machines, master, 1971 Mar; 9.30; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - 4-Master Dubbings - M.V. Mathews, 1968 Jan 4; 9.31; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - M.V. Mathews, PB 250, 1966 Mar 26 - Jun 25; 9.32; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Running Man, Elephants, Scales, Mistakes - 1st dub, 1973 Mar; 9.33; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Scales master, 1973 Jan 21; 9.34; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - 3-master dubbings - M.V. Mathews, 1968 Jan 4; 9.35; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Stockholm tape - copy, 9.36; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Pictures / Daisy / Speech Sings / Elephants / Shepard's Tones Risset, 9.37; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Illustrations for graphic compositions paper, master copy; Grenadier-Johnny, International Lullaby, 1967 Mar; 9.38; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Graphic composition demonstration tape, 9.39; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Jon Appleton, The Sydsing Camklang, 1976; 10.01; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Swansong and Scale and Melody Study, master, 1966 Oct 5; 10.02; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Groove Sounds and Moore's layered demo, 10.03; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Transition timbre studies, Pavis master, 1977; 10.04; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Slider, 1967 Nov 11; 10.05; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Risset computer music, 10.06; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Gabriel - Ravel - Webern - Ward, master, 1976 Mar 27; 10.07; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Sampling, 1964; 10.08; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Emmanuel Ghent, Brazen, 10.09; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Music I - Silver Scale, 1957 May; 10.10; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Groove Orchestra, 1st dub, 1973 Oct 28; 10.11; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Emmanuel Ghent, Entelechy, 1972 Apr 29; 10.12; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Emmanuel Ghent - Dualities, Brass, Phosphones, 10.13; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Emmanuel Ghent: Entelechy, viola and computer generated tape (DBx encoded), 10.14; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Emmanuel Ghent: Program Music 19, No. 3 ("Little Changes"), 10.15; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Ussochevsky - Colloquy, 10.16; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Emmanuel Ghent: Battery Park, Danger: High Voltage, etc., 10.17; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Slider master, 1965 Mar 7; 10.18; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - 1 - Master Dubbings - M.V. Mathews, 1967 Dec 29; 10.19; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Schubert - Japanese transition, master, 1966 Oct 5; 10.20; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - New scales, 1984 Jan 23; 10.21; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Pierce scales, Alyson Reeves, 1984 Aug 2; 10.22; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - International lullaby, master, 1966 Aug 24; 10.23; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - European master tape, 1963 Jun; 10.24; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Berkeley lecture, M.V. Mathews, Bell Labs, 1968 Mar 30; 10.25; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - ACM lecture - tape B, 1969 Jan 25; 10.26; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - ACM lecture, tape A, 10.27; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Tenney -Stochastic Quartet, master, 10.28; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Ampex test tape, 10.29; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Annotated Stockholm tape, 1981 Sep 11; 10.30; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Stockholm demo, 1985 Sep; 10.31; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - PB 250, Tenney, Mathews, 1965 Oct 1; 10.32; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - [Monaurl?] Graphic Scores demonstration, 10.33; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Slider - working tape #2, 1967 Nov 5; 10.34; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Play Song, 10.35; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Missa Brevis, Vladimir Ussachevsky, Kyrie/Sanctus/Benedictus, 10.36; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - 2 - master dubbings - M.V. Mathews, 1967 Dec 29; 10.37; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
    - Ravel F Quartet, 3rd movement, master, 1975 Mar 1; 11.01; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Boodleheimer Variations -- Pierce, 11.02; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Violin resonance demo tape, 11.03; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Birthday improvisation, master, 1970 Apr 2; 11.04; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Pierce and Matthews, non-harmonic sounds, 1979 May; 11.05; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Webern demo, 11.06; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Groove - M.V. Mathews; Improvising Machines; master, 1971 Jan; 11.07; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Mathews, PB 250 studies, 1965 Jul 13-17; 11.08; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Horizons demo, 11.09; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - 30 tone samples, master, 1971 Jul; 11.10; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Groove Orchestra, 100 Hz, master, 1973 Oct 28; 11.11; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Groove Orchestra, 50 Hz, master, 1973 Oct 28; 11.12; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Stretched octaves, 1978 Dec; 11.13; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Master - Gabriella, Ward, Ravel, Weber, 1975 Dec - 1976 Jan; 11.14; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Gabriela, Ward, Ravel, Webern - master, 1976 Feb 8; 11.15; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Webern, 6 Bagatellen, master, 1977 Jun 19; 11.16; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Ravel, F Quart.; Bach, Fuga I, 1975 Mar 5 and 8; 11.17; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Ravel F Quartet, 3rd m, 1975 Mar 3; 11.18; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Ravel, F Quartet, 1975 Feb 22; 11.19; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Bach, Fuga I, master, 1974 Nov 12; 11.20; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Resonated speech, 11.21; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Speech tape library copy with voice annotation, 11.22; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Electronic violin and resonators, 11.23; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Bach Fuga I, master, 1974 Nov 24; 11.24; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Bach, Fuga I, master, 1975 Feb 23 and Mar 8; 11.25; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Middle sections, Guttman-Mathews, master recording, long periods, 1961 Jan 10; 11.26; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Risset pieces, 1968; 11.27; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Mathews, Graphic I, 1966 Sep 6 and 8; 11.28; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Best dubbing of dialogues and phases -- Tenney, 1964 Apr 17; 11.29; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Violin tone samples, 1970 Jan 28; 11.30; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Gabrile - test slurs, 1975 Jun; 11.31; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Appleton - synclavier, 11.32; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Slider - M.V. Mathews, 11.33; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Electronic violin samples, and brasses and strings, 11.34; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Risset - Mutations, Little Boy, Scheenbergiana, 11.35; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Risset, Gift Study, 1974; 11.36; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Master Tapes - Elephants Can Graze, February 1972; 11.37; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Bach - Fuga I - Master, November 23 1974; 11.38; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Musical Styles Examples, December 1977; 11.39; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Ravel for Film, DBX, 12.01; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Olson synthesizer demo, 12.02; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Baden demo, DBX, 12.03; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Gerald Strang, synclavions, 12.04; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Stretched timbre demo, 12.05; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Speech synthesis comp, master, 1977-1979; 12.06; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Tests of 4B Machine, 12.07; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Transition timbre studies, 12.08; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Appleton-Pierce scale, Duo for Oscar, 12.09; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Risset paradoxes, 12.10; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Dumb ways to play intelligent machines, 12.11; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Pictures at an Exposition, Groove, F.R. Moore, 12.12; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
    - Molly Thompson, Knife Songs, concert recording, master, 1996 Oct 24; 12.13; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 12)
    - Buenos Aires History I, Mathews, 1992 Jun 9; 12.14; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Wild and Reckless Place, digital copies of master and mixed, 1992 Oct 12; 12.15; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - A Wild and Reckless Place, 1992 Jun 5; 12.16; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Max Mathews, 2000 Dec 9; 12.17; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Max Mathews, scanned synthesis, 2000 Nov 9; 12.18; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Paradoxes, sound catalog, concerto, Mathews, 1992 Jun 9; 12.19; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Bells of Hell, Wild and Reckless, 1993 May-Jun and Oct 10; 12.20; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Buenos Aires concert, 12.21; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Material for history CD of computer music, 12.22; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - MVM examples, 12.23; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - 3 symphonic states copy, orchestra only, Boulanger, 1997 May 23; 12.24; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Pacific Rimbombo master tape, 1993 Nov 20; 12.25; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Bauman history cassette, 1992 Jun 9; 12.26; 1 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - Unknown performance, 12.27; 2 audiocassette(s) (DAT) (Box 12)
    - J. C. Risset Sound Examples I, tracks 1-55, 1998 Feb; 13.01; 1 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
    - Rogersnd, 1994 Dec 12; 13.02; 1 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
    - J. C. Risset, Sound Examples II, tracks 1-48, 1998 February; 13.03; 1 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
    - J. C. Risset, Illusions, 1999; 13.04; 1 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
    - J. C. Risset, Sound Examples I, tracks 56-81, 1998 Feb; 13.05; 1 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
    - J. C. Risset, Sound Examples II, tracks 49-61, 1998 Feb; 13.06; 1 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
    - Computer Music Currents 13, disc and booklet [2 copies], 13.07; 2 optical disc(s) (CD) (Box 13)
  - Moving images
    - Papillons by Lillian F. Schwartz, 1973; 12.28; 2 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - Googolplex by Lillian F. Schwartz, 1972; 12.29; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - Original - cello string film, 12.30; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - Copy - cello string film, 12.31; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - Mutations (video: Lillian Schwartz; Audio: Jean-Claude Risset), 1972; 12.32; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
      - Mutations. Video: Lilian Schwartz. Audio: Jean-Claude Risset. (16mm film-to-tape transfer, 1/10/2006), 1972; 12.42; 1 videotape(s) (MiniDV) (Box 12)
    - Pixiliation by Lillian Schwartz and Ken Knowlton, music by Gershon Kingsley, 1970; 12.33; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - Metamorphosis by Lillian Schwartz and Ken Knowlton, 1974; 12.34; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - Apotheosis by Lillian Schwartz, music by F. Richard Moore; Affinities by Lillian Schwartz, music by F. Richard Moore; Enigma by Lillian Schwartz and Ken Knowlton, music by F. Richard Moore, 1972; 12.35; 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
    - AT&T Bell Labs, Shepard and Zajac, "Two Paradoxes", 1986 Feb 21; 12.36; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 12)
    - Sound examples for USA 1983 demonstration, 1983 Oct 13; 12.37; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 12)
    - A Musical Demonstration of the Mathews Conductor Program, 12.38; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 12)
    - Current Directions in Computer Music Research, Mathews, 12.39; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 12)
    - Olympiad: a film by Lillian Scwartz, composer Max Matthews [sic] (16mm film to tape transfer, 8/21/2006], 1973; 12.41; 1 videotape(s) (MiniDV) (Box 12)
      - Olympiad (16mm film-to-tape transfer at Monaco for Pacific Film Archive, 4/26/2006), 1973; 12.40; 1 videotape(s) (MiniDV) (Box 12)
- Oversize items
  - Muscial score, Philippe Manoury: "En Echo pour sorano & station temps-reel, d'apres des textes d'Emmanuel Hocquard."
  - Poster for seminar and concert featuring Max Mathews, Jean Claude Risset, and John Chowning (2 copies)
- Computer files, circa 1979-2011; Accession ARCH-2014-082; 269.2 gigabyte(s)
  - 2 Maxtor External Hard Drives (Box 1)